<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<item>
	<date>February 27, 2002</date>
	<publisher>The New York Times</publisher>
	<author>Denise Grady</author>
	<title>Baby Spared Mother's Fate by Genetic Tests as Embryo</title>
	<category>Health</category>
	<content>A 30-year-old woman who is very likely to develop a rare form of Alzheimer's disease before she turns 40 has had a baby girl who will be spared that fate because she was genetically screened as an embryo before being implanted in her mother's womb, doctors are reporting. 
The case is a medical milestone, the first use of genetic testing to prevent an early onset form of Alzheimer's disease. But some find it ethically disturbing because within a few years the mother will probably become unable to take care of her daughter, who will witness her deterioration and death. 
The 30-year-old woman, who carried a rare gene making it almost certain she will develop Alzheimer's, wanted to have a child but hoped to avoid passing on the bad gene. So she sought preimplantation diagnosis. In that procedure, embryos are created in the laboratory from the mother's eggs and the father's sperm and are tested genetically. Only healthy embryos are implanted in the mother's uterus. 
The case is being described today in The Journal of the American Medical Association by Dr. Yury Verlinsky and his associates from two private clinics in Chicago (see footnote 1). 
In a commentary (see footnote 2) article accompanying Dr. Verlinsky's report, &lt;font color="#0000ff"&gt;&lt;a  href="http://bioethics.ucdavis.edu/rloewy" target="_blank"&gt;Dr. Roberta Springer Loewy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt; and &lt;font color="#0000ff"&gt;&lt;a  href="http://women.ucdmc.ucdavis.edu/obgyn/2nd_template/Faculty/Doctors/Towner.htm"  targe="_blank" &gt;Dr. Dena Towner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt; wrote that the mother "most likely will not be able to care for or even recognize her child in a few years." Dr. Towner is director of the &lt;font color="#0000ff"&gt;&lt;a  href="http://women.ucdmc.ucdavis.edu/obgyn/prenatal.html-ssi" target="_blank" &gt;prenatal diagnosis center at the University of California at Davis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;, and Dr. Loewy is a bioethicist there. 
In an interview, Dr. Loewy said that it was laudable for the mother to try to protect her child from illness but that the child's physical health was not her only responsibility. 
"I'm not trying to pounce on this poor woman," Dr. Loewy said, but she added that she thought it would be traumatic for the child to watch the mother's slow decline and that if this same woman "wanted to adopt, our society essentially holds the position that, gee, no, we wouldn't let her do this, wouldn't let her subject a child to this. But because it's coming from her own loins, this is something we shouldn't have a say about?" 
Dr. William Thies, (see footnote 3) vice president of medical and scientific affairs for the &lt;font color="#0000ff"&gt;&lt;a  href="http://search.alz.org/mainpage.htm" target="_blank" &gt; Alzheimer's Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;, said: "It's a discussion being held in absence of any data. Does this end up being harmful to the child? Nobody knows." 
Dr. Loewy also said that society as a whole should consider whether this kind of treatment was the best use of limited medical resources. 
In a case like that of Dr. Verlinsky's patient, each effort to begin a pregnancy costs more than $12,000. Insurance coverage varies. 
Dr. Verlinsky said he had no qualms about helping the woman and her husband. "It's totally up to the patient," he said. 
As for the child's losing her mother, he said that many children were brought up by single parents, and that this family would be no different. Dr. Verlinsky said, too, that the couple had not made their decision in "a moment of emotion," but had had weeks and months to mull it over, because the medical procedures they went through in order to conceive take time. 
Asked whether the couple would have gone ahead and had children anyway if preimplantation diagnosis was not available, Dr. Verlinsky said he did not know. 
The couple were not available for interviews, he said. 
The new report does not apply to most families with Alzheimer's disease, because the form the woman has accounts for less than 1 percent of all cases. The type of testing the woman had is not done for the more common types of Alzheimer's disease, which develop much later in life, and in which the role of particular genes is far less clear. 
Dr. Thies said, "It's important for people to recognize that this does not represent a strategy that will have much of a public health impact." 
The woman described by Dr. Verlinsky and his colleagues carries a rare genetic mutation that makes it almost certain she will develop Alzheimer's disease in her 30's. Her sister, who also has the mutation, developed Alzheimer's symptoms at age 38. The gene is involved in the formation of the tangled protein deposits, known as amyloid plaques, found in the brain in people with Alzheimer's disease. People who carry certain mutations in the gene nearly always develop dementia. 
The sister with Alzheimer's declined so much mentally that she had to be moved to an assisted-living center. A brother also had the mutation and began suffering memory problems at 35. Their father died at 42, with psychological and memory problems. 
People who do not want the expense and trouble of preimplantation diagnosis can become pregnant naturally and then have the fetus tested via &lt;font color="#0000ff"&gt;&lt;a  href="http://www.amniocentesis.org/" target="_blank" &gt;amniocentesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt; or another procedure, &lt;font color="#0000ff"&gt;&lt;a  href="http://www.marchofdimes.com/professionals/681_1165.asp" target="_blank" &gt; chorionic villus sampling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/font&gt;. But if the fetus has a genetic disease, the parents must decide whether to end the pregnancy. Preimplantation testing is particularly appealing to people who want to avoid abortion. 
The technique has been used to prevent many diseases, including hemophilia, sickle cell anemia, muscular dystrophy, Tay-Sachs disease, cystic fibrosis and Huntington's disease. It should not be used just to pick embryos of a particular sex, according to an opinion issued this month by a professional group, the American Society for Reproductive Medicine. 
</content>
	<footnotes>
<notes>1. International Working Group on Preimplantation Genetics. Preimplantation genetic diagnosis: experience of three thousand clinical cycles: report of the 11th Annual Meeting of the International Working Group on Preimplantation Genetics, in association with 10th International Congress of Human Genetics,Vienna, May 15, 2001. Reprod BioMed Online. 2001;3:49-53. 
2. Verlinsky Y, Rechitsky S, Verlinsky O, et al. Preimplantation diagnosis for p53 tumor suppressor gene mutations. Reprod BioMed Online. 1;2:102-105. 
3. Verlinsky Y, Rechitsky S, Schoolcraft W, Strom C, Kuliev A. Preimplantation diagnosis for Fanconi anemia combined with HLA matching. JAMA. 2001;285:3130-3133.
</notes>
</footnotes>
</item>